<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A Letter to a friend concerning the present state of affairs</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 43KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B25892</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">27395848</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205737</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240873718</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1645A</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">27395848</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B25892)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205737)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1725:38)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A Letter to a friend concerning the present state of affairs</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1693]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Caption title.</note>
                  <note>Text begins: That impatient inquisitiveness so natural to our Country-men, rises in most people with the Sap in the Spring ...</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702.</term>
               <term type="geographic_name">Great Britain --  Politics and government --  1689-1702.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2014-05 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-08 </date>
            <label>Kate Allen</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205737:1"/>
            <head>A LETTER to a Friend concerning the Present State of Affairs.</head>
            <p>THAT impatient inquisitiveness so natural to our Country-men, rises in most People with the Sap in the Spring, and in such an Age as ours, when <hi>Fleets</hi> and <hi>Armies</hi> must move at that Time, when <hi>Descents</hi> and <hi>Invasions</hi> are become familiar, and as duely to be expected as <hi>May,</hi> I must confess that Season seems naturally to rouze our thoughts and expectations, yet out of the common road I find you al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways possest with an <hi>Octobtr</hi> Curiosity; I do not say I wonder at it, for to make use of a Country Comparison; it is not the richest Manure in Summer nor the <hi>April-showers,</hi> will bring the Fruit to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection; previous to this must be the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumnal Care, the well pruning the Tree, the cutting away the false, and useless branches, opprest with which, the good ones cannot bear: Your Curiosity there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I think well tim'd, I wish you had made no mistake in the Person that was to satisfie it. This is not only the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per season of enquiry after what has, and may be done, but I fear the last and only Opportunity given us to act in for our preservation, I wish it were as evident, as true, that now or never effectual means must be taken for the support of this Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, if these Kingdoms are to be rescued from Misery and Confusion.</p>
            <p>What is it can be called a publick Calamity that we are not just falling in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to if not already in? Are we not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaged in a War with a potent Forreign Enemy? Have we not a disputed Title at home, and no Agreement even in the Protestant part of the Royal Family amongst us? Are there not Taxes that rake up all the Wealth of the Nation? And is there not a management that squanders it as fast abroad? Is not our blood as well as money spent for others? And are not both managed with the like discretion? How tedious might a man be in the recital of our ill Circumstan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces? Have we not most dangerous Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions within our selves? I mean not some for, others against, this Establishment, but I speak of the Division, not to say Treacheries amongst those that pretend they would support it, can there be Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumstances requiring a nicer Judgment and Penetration, and what <hi>Eyes</hi> have we to see by, what <hi>Heads</hi> to determine with but those of <hi>Strangers,</hi> and almost we may say, what <hi>Hands</hi> to act by but the same? 'Tis true we endeavour to save <hi>Holland</hi> by <hi>English,</hi> but I fear the project is to preserve <hi>England</hi> by <hi>Dutch;</hi> but a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove all the rest when the Disease is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>most desperate we distrust the Physitian, the Nation is environed with Enemies and Dangers, and we are jealous (not without Reason) of our Ministers, and those that govern, the present King. All People begin to Consider him as a For<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reigner, and more so by inclination than by Birth, and the herd of Fools begin to look upon the Late King as a mislead Man, yet an English-Man; but in a word to conclude with the worst of symptoms, they begin too, to compare the Deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verer with him from whom we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered, and to my grief, a few Words will too far justifie these Fears and Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>strusts; was not the foundation of this
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:205737:2"/> Government Resormation, is there any thing rectified? Was not the foundation of this Government mismanagement in others, yet is their any body punished? Was not the Motive to this Government Change, yet every thing is almost as it was? A great Revolution as it is called and nothing altered, the same Maxims of Government are asserted, and the same sort of People looked after to put them in execution; nay, to be more sure, ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny of the individual Persons are again employed: If there be any Alteration it is only in this, all the fine and hidden stroaks in King <hi>Charles</hi>'s Reign towards Arbitrary Power, are now (by the help of some <hi>forreign</hi> Talents) exposed to view in a broad <hi>Dutch</hi> Shape and Cha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racter.</p>
            <p>Tho' I know you expect plain deal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from me, yet these Truths may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps surprise you; prudent Men have hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>therto been desirous to hide these things from the World, as it was and must still be the business of every thinking and ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nest man to preserve this Government, so the concealing what might lose us the Inclination, and Hearts of the People, was the duty of all well-wishers to it; but our Circumstances allow not of those managements now, too much of our own blood, of our wealth, has been spent in continued follies which cannot be longer kept secret. Our condition must now be truly stated, and fully known, that proper and speedy remedies may be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed.</p>
            <p>The Task you have imposed I fear is too big for me, every Year will make it more difficult to give true <hi>Idaea's</hi> of the present Circumstances of Affairs, or to offer to make Scheams, or lay down Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods for our future security, it is too evident our Dangers encrease, and that our Enemies multiply; I wish we could believe the number of our Friends did not diminish, or that all those that ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear such were true.</p>
            <p>In order to obey you, I have resolved in the first place to examine impartially what has been writ of All hands in those Pamphlets seem most to deserve Consi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration, my design is to side with Truth wherever I find it, and to expose all false Reasonings as far as I am able; and this way I hope I shall in some measure an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swer your expectation, and not be whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly unserviceable to those who desire to be prepared, honestly to stand by the true Interest of their Country in this Criti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Moment either for its <hi>Settlement</hi> or <hi>Ruine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The first Paper I shall consider has for Title, <hi>The Pretenc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>s of the French Inva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion Examined;</hi> it has at least the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>probation of a Secretary of State, being Licensed by publick Authority, and sent into the World with an Air almost of <hi>Infallibility.</hi> A Man presumes well of himself, that puts this in the Front of his Work, [<hi>For the Information of the Peopl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of</hi> England.]</p>
            <p>I wish they were well informed, it is d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ngerous for them to be much longer in the dark, but whoever undertakes that great Task, (to inform the People) ought to be very candid in Matters of Fact, he is bound in Writing to those strict Rules of an Oath, <hi>the Truth, the whole Truth, and noth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>g but the Truth;</hi> all thi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>gs asserted by him, must be as pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>in, as true, no positions laid down but what are undeniable, and the Consequen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of them natural and easie, nothing must be made use of, either to palliate Matters of Fact, or to disguise them, neither should any the least Circumstance be concealed, Rhetorick and Sophistical Argumentation are undeniable Proofs a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst any man that makes use of them
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:205737:2"/> that he designs not to inform, but abuse the People.</p>
            <p>If these Maxims I have laid down are true, I doubt not to make it appear, that this Author (whoever he be) is not less out of the way (tho' with the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority of <hi>this Secretary</hi>) than an other, who not long ago had the Sanction of <hi>the other Office,</hi> for maintaining K. <hi>William</hi>'s Title to the Crown, by <hi>Conquest.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It were to be wish'd that those would not write for a Cause, who betray in what they give the Publick, that in Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Opinion they are against it, nothing sure but a good Place could so guide the hand against the heart, which some men (with very nice Consciences) can hold in that Government whose ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry foundation they opposed at first and have always since been undermining.</p>
            <p>One would take the Author of this Pamphlet to be in such Circumstances, he declares for this Government, but whoever examines what he writes, will find he would give it a false bottom, that cannot support it, I think I shall be able to shew that all his Arguments for it, are more conclusive the other way, whatever his Intentions are, I confess his Maxims and Arguments would inform me, that I were obliged in Conscience to help the Late King to his Crown again, or to let him take it at pleasure.</p>
            <p>To explain the Title of a Prince, to whom the People in the most solemn manner gave a Crown, and from whom he received it with this Expression, <hi>I thankfully accept,</hi> he makes such a Hodg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>podge of <hi>Succession, Election</hi> and <hi>Conquest,</hi> that no man knows what he means, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be free-born, or a slave, if we were desirous to have a State breed, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sembling that of St. <hi>Athanasius</hi> of all mankind, we should make choyce of this Informer; all that I can conceive of his aim is this, that either he would make the <hi>plainest</hi> and most <hi>natural</hi> Title in the world <hi>doubtful,</hi> and <hi>unintelligible,</hi> or that out of his three <hi>incomprehensibles</hi> he would ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e one Almighty.</p>
            <p>Give me leave to repeat to you what our great Champion undertakes for us; he engages to answer the pretended Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tives of those that would endeavour the Restoration of the Late King, <hi>p.</hi> 2. <hi>l.</hi> 8. Now these he divides into Four Heads, 1. <hi>Repairing the Injury done to the Late King.</hi> 2. <hi>Delivering us from the Oppres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion we suffer under the Present King.</hi> 3. <hi>The setling the Government upon its own Basis.</hi> 4. <hi>Securing the Protestant Religion f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>r all future Ages.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I fear I make use of too gay a Simile for so solemn a Subject, but I think it would extreamly suprise if a passionate Lover should endeavour to make his Court to his Mistriss, by going about to prove that she was not deformed or monstrous, that she was undeservedly censured in her Reputation, and that her Constitution was not ruined by scandalous Diseases; though all this were well made out, I believe the <hi>Phillis</hi> would not think her self much obliged to him for his pains.</p>
            <p>I cannot but conceive this pretended Lover of the State has done something like this, he begins by a supposition of all that could be Objected against the worst of Governments, and then pretends to shew that such things are falsly layd to our Charge, what more injurious suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sition can be hinted, than one Mans right is founded upon an Injury done to an other? What can be more reflecting than that a Prince should oppress a Nation, espe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in our Case, when he pretends to the Merits of a Deliverer? What more dangerous insinuations than the subver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion of a Government from its old Basis, and the National Religion endangered?</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205737:3"/>
            <p>I must confess I little expected to see such weighty Charges against the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, Licensed by a Secretary of State; to say no more, especially when the Defence for it I think is so weak, that (to make use of the Authors own Expression at the bottom of the seventh Page) <hi>We ought to complain of such Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jurers, who raise the Sto<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ms they cannot ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pease, and a Devil they cannot lay.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>First then, these are the Words he puts into the mouth of those that argue for the Establishment of the Late King, that <hi>The Late King was unjustly deprived of his Birth-right by his Subjects, who by Nature, and Oaths, were bound to defend him in the poss<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ssion of it, and now that he comes to demand his own, all that ever were his Subjects, must either assist, or at least not oppose him,</hi> p. 2. l. 18.</p>
            <p>Now pray Sir, consider how he ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>solves Mankind from these Tyes, which he supposes Nature and Religion has im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>posed upon them.</p>
            <p>He begins this great Work thus, <hi>(Let it be considered that all the Late King</hi>'s <hi>Sufferings were owing to, and caused by the Councils of his Popish Priests, and the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gots of that perswasion, Pr<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>testants were n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t the aggressors, he might have kept his pos<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>session to this day undisturbed, if he had not made such open and bold Attempts up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on our Laws, Religion and Properties, so that he was the first and only cause of his own Sufferings; and why should Millions be involved in blood and ruine who are perfectly innocent of doing this injury,</hi> p. 2. l. 24.</p>
            <p>These few Lines, give us a taste of what we have to expect from his since<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerity, the Contradictions follow so close, and the false Reasonings are so evident, that one can suppose no reasonable aim in them, but giving up the Argument in the ten first Lines of his Plea, he ought to satisfie us that no wrong was done the Late King, and he concludes the first paragraph with this (that those that were innocent of doing him the Injury, should not in Justice be punished for it.)</p>
            <p>I cannot, I must confess, but imagin the Author is one that relies upon mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing use of this Argument, when it will be more proper than it is in this place, and so it runs much in his head.</p>
            <p>I must farther observe to you, it's some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing extraordinary that he who writes <hi>(for the Information of the People of En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland)</hi> should let us know that all the Late King's Sufferings were owing to, and caused by his Popish Priests; and the Bigots of that perswasion, and then averrs within three Lines, <hi>That he was the first and only Cause of his own Suffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings,</hi> with this notable Argument in con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clusion, <hi>And why should Millions be invol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved in blood and ruine, who are perfectly innocent of doing this injury?</hi> To this last part I only appeal to the Authors own Conscience, how many Sermons he has approvingly assisted at, where the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple have been told from the Pulpit, that the <hi>Fire, Dutch War,</hi> and <hi>Plague,</hi> were just Punishments; nay that all the <hi>Plagues of Egypt</hi> were due to <hi>them</hi> and <hi>their Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sterity,</hi> for the Injuries done to <hi>K. Charles the First.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I suppose he might have a meaning, when he declares the Late King was mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lead and influenced by Popish Councils; it in some sort excuses him, and inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mates a Remedy that might easily have been attained in a way natural to our Constitution, the removal of such its Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>visers and Counsellors, which had it been practised in time, would have prevented those unfortunate Disputes, and might yet prevent others, if now thought of: But it is plain (though by chance in the next Line he declares him the first and sole Actor in his own Tragedy, that in
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:205737:3"/> the whole Course of his Treatise, he makes Kings <hi>unaccountable</hi>) and the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple without any expedient <hi>sacrificed</hi> to <hi>perpetual Oppression,</hi> unless the Prince ceases of himself to oppress or govern; if so, in whatsoever, was a Force upon the Late King, by this principle he must confess an injury done to him, and who owns an injury done, cannot deny but that a reparation is required by divine and hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane Laws.</p>
            <p>Now Sir we shall soon come to the point, there is a pretty word in fashion, <hi>(Abdication)</hi> a word of wonderful effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cacy, it settles a world of tender Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sciences. The Late King has Abdicated, and those Men, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 22. <hi>(obliged before</hi> (as he says himself) <hi>by all sacred and civil Tyes to venture their Lives for his support)</hi> become in a moment the last of Villains, if they assist him in the least, if they lift up their hands they must sight against him: This indeed is the Corner-stone of the whole Fabrick, the only expedient our Author and his Party have to make their Passive Obedience, and Loyalty consistent with a place un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der King <hi>William;</hi> no wonder this is la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured for so often in the same page, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 14. <hi>We did not make the Throne va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cant, p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 20. <hi>He left us in Anarchy, and we provided for our selves in the best manner such a Conjuncture would allow, p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 31. Somebody must govern, when he would not, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>We did not force him to go away in Disguise.</hi> I must confess this were Abdication well proved. But when we come to put this Term in plain English, (deserting the Throne, and quitting the Government) and to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sider of it we shall find the matter of fact was not so, nay our Author himself (as I shall shew you when I come to repeat his words) is pleased to tell us direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 10. the Late King did not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sert his Throne, and to lay it down for a fundamental, that it was not in his power to renounce the Government, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 2.</p>
            <p>I must take the liberty to say there is nothing so Priest like, and unbecoming Men of Honour, Integrity and Reason, as upon this occasion to dodge about and cover <hi>equivocating Loyalty</hi> with this Noti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of <hi>Abdication,</hi> even <hi>Sherlock</hi>'s well-bred Doctrine, I prefer to this of complying with what God is pleased to bless and prosper, long may that Argument conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nue for us, but of all men I should think we were the most unfortunate if our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stablishment were built upon either of these Foundations, if so I fear the Late King if ever he return, will soon con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince us he did not <hi>Abdicate,</hi> and if he take a seasonable opportunity, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny will see the <hi>guiding</hi> hand of <hi>Providence</hi> in it. Upon the first Article we lose our Author and his <hi>Legions,</hi> upon the second the <hi>Doctor</hi> and the Tribe of <hi>Levi,</hi> and who not; for who would resist the Will of the Almighty declared in favour of a Prince who had the better of the Lay. The <hi>Groom-Porter</hi> follows the <hi>Church,</hi> and then all's lost.</p>
            <p>But we must give the Author thanks he has quoted such opinions for our just Title to the Crown that all good men must respect <hi>pag.</hi> 3. <hi>lin.</hi> 4. <hi>We did not</hi> (says he) <hi>make the Throne vacant, but the late Arch-bishop and other Peers at</hi> Guild-Hall, <hi>believed he had left it void or else they would not without his consent have seis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on the Administration of the Government;</hi> the late Arch-bishop thought he had left it void, and this Arch-bishop thinks it well fitted, how can a <hi>Son</hi> of the <hi>Church</hi> have any scruples?</p>
            <p>But it so falls out the late Arch-bishop is now of another mind, and this Arch-bishop may change his mind as our Epis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copal
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:205737:4"/> Secretary has changed his mind, notwitstanding, what Sir <hi>John Denham</hi> said of a Saint, I may apply upon this occasion <hi>(yet the Church stands uninfected)</hi> I wish I could find the <hi>Government</hi> were like to stand <hi>unshaken</hi> too, as that seems in dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, I shall endeavour to shew that our Undertaker and his Disciples are build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing contrary to Scripture and sence, upon sandy Foundations, and to prove it true from his own Maxims and his Self-con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tradictions. I take this Author to be a Master-workman, tho' I believe he came in at the last hour for he writes with authority, is supported by authority, and the publick authority that is given to him makes me apt to confound the Secretary with the Author, but this I am sure of, had I voted against the Vacancy of the Throne, had I voted against the Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, or if I now pretended to be a Friend to King <hi>William</hi> and his Establish<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, I would have refused my Name to the countenance of this Paper, as to the most idle piece of Sophistry that ever ventur'd to shew it self in publick.</p>
            <p>To convince you of what I have said, that his Arguments are directly opposite to his Profession and the present Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment, I must desire you to observe these passages (<hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 22.) <hi>I will not en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire now whether these Subjects who are so zealous for his return were not bound to do more than they did to keep him in the Throne while he had it;</hi> and afterwards (<hi>he went away while a Treaty was on foot, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but a Treaty can restore him fairly, which he never yet offered,</hi> p. 4. last Lines, <hi>We did not force him to go away in Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise, and if he will force himself upon us again by French Dragoons and Irish Cut-throats, we may and must oppose him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Here our Author you see takes occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion to accuse the Late Kings Friends and Subjects, for not defending him in the Throne while he was in possession of it, had it been my design to disswade man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind from endeavouring to restore the Late King to the Throne. I should have thought a great while, before I had found out this strong Argument against it, that Englishmen had neglected their duty in not venturing their Lives for his preservation in it, but this Critical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>former has so nice a distinction, that he can tell you to a moment when you may fight for, and against the same person; though I take him to be a great Judge of the proper season, methods and ways, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 5. of <hi>transferring Allegiance,</hi> yet I must say he is a little forgetful of his premises, and not over exact in his ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gumentation; never man had so just a Title to much Wit, by having so little Memory: He forgets that but few lines before in the same half page, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 3. he has absolved the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> and those that joyned with him, from any designs against the Rights of the Late King, <hi>(Now but defensive Arms</hi> (says he) <hi>were taken up by some few, and by a for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reign Prince only to cover their heads, while the Grievances were fairly redressed, not to take away his Rights but to secure our own, nor did the Prince of</hi> Orange, <hi>or these Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen divest or deprive him of his Throne)</hi> How then could any man be faulty in not defending what was never attacqu'd, how could men think of fighting against such Lambs, that only took up defensive Arms to cover their heads while Grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vances were fairly redrest, it was being of opinion with the Author that made them slip this opportunity he says they should have laid hold of, believing a Son-in-Law and Daughter came not to invade a Fathers Right but to secure their own. You see Sir how dexterously this Master of true reasoning has accused and justified in a breath. There is this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205737:4"/> farther to be said for their excuse if they had or ought to have had the will, they wanted the power, which will appear when we come to consider the Charge our Author makes against the Late King, the first Article of which is for disbanding the Army.</p>
            <p>But how shall these Gentlemen be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swaded (allowing they lay under an Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligation to have ventur'd their Lives for the preservation of the late King in the Throne) that it is now the most horrid of attempts a mortal sin in them, to en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavour his restitution to it, I must con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fess, I think no body but this Author, who writes with more than <hi>Poetick Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cense</hi> in his Prose, would attempt the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monstration, and in my opinion he makes it out backwards, as Witches say the Lords-Prayer.</p>
            <p>It is undenyable he confesses such a Right and Title in the late King, at the time of the Prince of <hi>Oranges</hi> Landing, that his Subjects might and should have defended by Arms, or else they deserv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed not his reproaches for their Neglect, the late King must then have forfeited that Right by some Act of his own since, or the Right must remain in him, and Subjects are under an obligation, or at least have a liberty to endeavour to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure him his Right, wherefore any at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt for him upon this Foundation, I am sure can neither be Treason against Reason or Religion.</p>
            <p>Now Sir we must consider what the Author pretends the late King has done since, that can alter the Case thus from one extream to another.</p>
            <p>In this same mysterious page he begins his Charge contained in these Articles, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>(he disbanded his Army, dissolv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed his Government, and as much as in him lay attempted to desert the Throne)</hi> it is plain that the only colour and pretence of Argument in this Rethorical piece of <hi>Forgism,</hi> is comprised as I have said be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in this single word <hi>Abdication,</hi> but how unfortunate is it for men of tender Consciences, that when all mankind were prepared to receive this informing Paper Licensed by our sole Secretaay, as no less than the sence of Church and State, they should find <hi>infallibility</hi> so soon <hi>contradict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> it self, for in the compass of twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty lines he in direct words tells us, as I mentioned before, that King <hi>James</hi> did not Abdicate, that the late King could not Abdicate, there can be no greater proof a man did not do a thing, than that he attempted in vain to do it, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 10. (<hi>And as much as in him lay at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempted to desert the Throne,</hi> and in ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>press words he says he could not do it, <hi>Now when a King and Queen are decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, submitted to, and own'd by Oaths, and all other Methods required, in such a Case the King is not at liberty to give up his powers, and the protection of us,</hi> p. 4. l. 2. So that by his own Confession this <hi>first</hi> and <hi>last</hi> Article of our Creed is only false in <hi>fact</hi> and in <hi>possibility,</hi> and this darling Word and Notion, by which a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lone a Loyal Man, or a Church-man can reconcile his Conscience to our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment our Author has himself destroyed, but some Commentators will accuse me of not having minded a passage, <hi>p.</hi> 3. <hi>l.</hi> 29. which does run thus, <hi>(a man may leave his Right when he pleases but may not take it again at his pleasure, especially not by force, and this most especially as to sove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raign power):</hi> I must again repeat the Words last quoted, <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>l.</hi> 2. <hi>Now when a King and Queen are declared and owned by Oaths,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>the King is not at liberty to give up his power and protection of us:</hi> if it were not for these last Words in the first Paragraph, <hi>most especially as to so<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign power,</hi> one would think he had
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205737:5"/> forgot he was speaking of a King own<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by Oaths, taken I believe by our Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor himself, which by his way of rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>soning I wonder he can absolve himself from. I cannot but confess I am not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to reconcile these Texts, but find<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing something so Sublime and Orthodox in the whole Treatise, I acquiesce and say no more, lest a doubt in this case, should make me pass for an Enemy to the Church.</p>
            <p>Now Sir as to the other Paragraph mentioned <hi>p.</hi> 4. <hi>last Line (He went away while a Treaty was on f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ot, and nothing but a Treaty can restore him fairly, which he never yet desired, we did not force him to go away in Disguise, and if he will force himself upon us again by French Dragoons and Irish Cut-throats, we may and must oppose him.)</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I own that the Author for once has dealt plainly with us, and made such a discovery of himself and Party, that no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>predestinated</hi> blindness can hin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der us from a thorough Knowledge of him and his Followers, if a Treaty may restore him fairly, and that our Author justly blames him for not having hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to offered it, sure the natural consequence is that whenever he offers one it will be unfair not to receive it. Now the business the late King has to Treat about, is on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Crown, of which he is to demand Restitution, to Address to the Present King for his Kingdom and his Sceptre, would in my mind be an extraordinary Application, who if he thought himself at liberty to take them, will hardly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive himself obliged to restore them: This Author's Eloquence will not per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>swade him to it; besides he forgets he has declared <hi>p.</hi> 4 <hi>l.</hi> 2. the present King is too far engaged, and that no King is at liberty to give up his power and the protection of Nations, is he then to treat with the People? Shall he too apply to them, who are guilty of Treason if they listen, and are only to be hang'd, drawn and quarter'd, if they have any Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>spondence with him? Where then (to make use of the fashionable Word, and to speak like a States-man) <hi>are the first Paces to be made</hi> towards this great Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gotiation? I think it must be begun with, and ended by our Author, for I find no body else will, or dare meddle with it; but he having the approbation of the Government in writing about it, cannot sure be reprehended by the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment if he engages in the Treaty. He will no doubt, when he brings back the late King fairly, make very good Conditions, for those that were the oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>casion of his going. But I am Block-head enough to think, that as a Well-wisher to the present Establishment (ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in respect of King or People) the Author was under no necessity of start<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this Notion of a Treaty, the result of which must be either, that the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sent King is to resign his Kingdoms, or that the People are to take back their Old One, and for his Reputation (in my poor thoughts) he could suffer in nothing more, than in mentioning a thing so fri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>volous and unpracticable: The <hi>Rehersal</hi> does not give us such a <hi>Turn of State</hi> in the Fate of the Kings of <hi>Brentford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>For the other part of the Text (we did not force him to go away in Dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guise) though what he would insinuate be but a weak and false support to the beloved Abdication, (as I shall endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour to shew in my next Letter if not this Post) yet as he has hapned to word it, I agree with him entirely, we did not indeed force the King away in Disguise, but forced him away publickly, attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Guards in great Solemnity.</p>
            <pb n="9" facs="tcp:205737:5"/>
            <p>If I am obliged to be tedious in my Observations, it is because never Man in so narrow a Compass gave such repeat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed occasions <hi>(if he will force himself upon us again by French Dragoons and Irish Cut-throats,</hi> says our Author, <hi>we may and must oppose him,</hi> what then, he may come when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever he thinks fit, with <hi>Swedes, Danes,</hi> and <hi>Polanders,</hi> and be heartily welcome; or if he pleases to come alone when <hi>R.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reymond</note> is Major, and <hi>K.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Killegreu</note> Admiral, and <hi>T.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Trevor</note> Chan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellor, and <hi>S.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seymor</note> Treasurer, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any Change in the Secre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taries Office, I doubt not he will be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiv'd with all imaginable Marks of Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty and Affection, though French Dra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>goons and Irish Cut-throats are sure to follow.</p>
            <p>I must take the liberty to repeat two or three more of his Sentences upon this Head, you have engaged me at your pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ril and must have patience, the Nation serves you as a great Example (finally, <hi>p.</hi> 5. <hi>l.</hi> 5. <hi>There is no injury to any but himself, and those who run into voluntary Exile with him by his being cut of posses<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. The Monarchy, the Law, the Church and Property are all in better Estate than in his Time, and all these with innumera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble private Persons must be irreparably in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jured by his Return in a Hostile manner</hi>) our Author one would think had been frighted as K. <hi>J</hi>— the First was in his Mothers Belly with a Sword; he hates War and Tumult, and by no means would have the late King return in a Hostile manner, Drums and Trumpets, Canons and Bombs are his aversion, but for Treaties and all other amicable Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods of bringing him back, those he of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mentions with great satisfaction, yet notwithstanding he tells us, <hi>the Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy, the Law, the Church, and Property, are all in a better Estate than in his Time;</hi> if so, why any Treaty? What is it we should Treat for?</p>
            <p>But Oh the <hi>Church!</hi> that Word seems more terrible to me than all the others just now mentioned; I think the very Name of it has frighted above half the Nation out of their senses for these three years last past; for my part, I meddle not with it, and wish it so settled and undisturbed, that it may not be so much as talked of more. As to our <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Property,</hi> which justly take the next place, I confess the Expectations raised by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi>'s Declaration are not answered, and I must own some Pamphlets writ by the other Party (which I have promised to speak impartially of, and to Treat as fair Enemies) have made me doubt whether they be in much better Estate than they were; this Sir we shall afterwards consider of. But for <hi>Monar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chy,</hi> that sort of Monarchy our Author means, and Explains in the Ninth Page, Hereditary and Successive Monarchy, how that comes to be in a better Estate by an Election of a Forreign Prince into the Throne, actually in possession of the Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power of another State, and this done by the solemn Choyce of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and the Suffrages of both Houses of Parliament, by which Choyce, not only the late King's Title and his pretended Sons is layd aside, but also the Princess of <hi>Denmark</hi> postponed, who I suppose has not Abdicated; how this confirms and puts Hereditary Successive Monarchy into a better Estate, I confess I cannot apprehend: I say no more now as to this part, but beg Pardon of the Author for speaking to that last, he puts first. I hope I shall not be Censured of ill breeding, or disrepect to <hi>Monarchy,</hi> in giving precedency to the <hi>Church,</hi> what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever be the Rank of <hi>Law</hi> and <hi>Property.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I have the ill Fortune to be able to
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205737:6"/> agree with no part of his Paragraph: This allowing an injury done to the late King upon all occasions, and these Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties by which he may seek to be fairly restored, all this together I confess would not please me, were I at the Head of the present Government; but his Argument in my Opinion is most false upon his own premises, <hi>(there is no injury do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e,</hi> (says our Author) <hi>to any but himself,, and th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>se who run into voluntary Exile with him by his being out of possession):</hi> Now by his leave, if there be an injury done to him, I think the injury very general, done to the whole Nation, who should have a feeling in any injury done to their right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful King; a King that has his Crown injuriously taken away from him, some<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>time or other will find a Party that will endeavour to redress that injury by Arms, and Civil intestine War in consequence will prove an injury, the whole and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry part of the Nation will sufficiently suffer by, besides the damage happens not alone to those he calls (voluntary Exiles) which if an injury be done the late King, I shall esteem honourable Martyrs for a justifiable Loyalty, but to all others who live by just scruples, debarred from pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick employments, and exposed as seve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral have been to the payment of double Taxes and other inconveniences.</p>
            <p>As yet you see I have but endeavour'd to shew you the false Argumentation of the Author, and have only brought his own Arguments against his own beloved Notion, though they sufficiently ridicule it. Yet Sir you must allow me to give you my own thoughts about this Abdi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, I shall endeavour to shew you in my next Letter, that all discourse about it, is vain and impertinent, and no way to the purpose as to the present Esta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blishment. What a sputter and pains are here taken to avoid the Confession of this Notorious Truth, that the People of <hi>England,</hi> (having an opportunity given them by the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> freely to assemble) bestowed the Crown upon him forfeited by the late King; many rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable Motives inclined them to this Choyce, and this not the least prevail<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Consideration, that from a Prince who had expressed such a care and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cern for theit Laws, Constitution and Liberty, when a Forreigner, it was rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sonable to expect a most tender regard to them when chosen King. As doubtless the Body of the Nation went upon just and reasonable Grounds, as the ends were reasonable, so the steps towards it were in my opinion in the utmost form of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stice, Equity and Prudence, and exactly adjusted to those ends, except in so far as they were byassed by the Author and his Party: But this I am sure of, and shall endeavour to make undeniably plain in my next, that those who will not own this Opinion, are Vipers nursed in the bosom of the Government, that will de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stroy it when ever they are warmed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to sufficient power to act with safety, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plying with, at least acting for a Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment a Man must disavow, makes him appear in my mind the lowest and most vile of Knaves; but this Excuse is to be made for some in Employment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongst us, that they seem prest into the service, though they have frankly owned their Opinion, and declared for Months together in the face of the World, their dislike to our Government; indeed if it be of absolute necessity for the welfare of a Government established as ours, that those be employed to support it, who were Ministers in the preceding Reign, or have opposed it to their utmost, and cannot, or will not, as we, own it right<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful and lawful, as the Notion seems con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary to common prudence, so let the
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205737:6"/> Principle be contrary to common sence, and a better foundation cannot be found than a Tory Abdication for a Government to cheat it self by, or for Knaves to fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nish themselves with pretences; but as I pretend to a sincerity, shall as little spare my friends as adversaries; I only wait to see the Election, so much talked of, the Popish Convert, reconverted in <hi>Hol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> chosen at the request of the Whiggs, for their Champion, to support the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>testant Religion, and the Liberties of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland;</hi> I only stay I say, to see this known Enemy of <hi>France</hi> thus sanctified, and then adopted by them, boldly to declar'd in the behalf of my Friends and Brethren the Whiggs, that of all Parties of Men that ever the World produc'd, they deserve the preference for folly a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#murp" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d knavery.</p>
            <p>I would be glad to know what Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment there is or can be in Nature, that I will not find authority for and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst, in this one comprehensive page: This Author I dare engage (provided it suits with his interest, and that of his Party) will find some piece of Gospel or Law, to satisfie his and their Consci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences in all Circumstances, and at all Times <hi>(&amp; factum valet quod fieri non de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>buit)</hi> will enable him to write such ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Treatise for the next ensuing Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, unless perhaps this may serve the turn, though indeed he will tell us in the New Piece, that we ought to have fought more obstinately for our King while he was in the Throne, but are ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liged (lest we make innocent people suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer by a War) to submit to any Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment that provides but an honest and able Secretary of State, fit, like <hi>Atlas</hi> alone to support the politick World.</p>
            <p>I was going to conclude, and like to have forgotten our Author in his great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>est Glory (where he appears indeed like the great Man I always took him for) raising Money without Parliament, giv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Pensions to Kings, and restoring for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feited Estates <hi>(if it be pleaded, that he who was born to a Kingdom, really wants subsistence; I reply, that if he would seek the Peace of Christendom, and of his late Subjects, he might by a fair Treaty set on foot, not only restore the Exiles, but have a sufficient and Honourable Maintenance from this Government):</hi> A Man would be well suppled with Matter, that had only these few Lines to Examine, but I shall leave large Gleanings for others, and only desire you to consider how kind a Friend our Author is to the Friends of this Government, and how fierce a Foe to the Enemies of it. Every day we see <hi>Jacobites</hi> handing about Declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions where no body is pardoned, not those they pretend they would pardon; and here our Author promises to all those that have been accessary to the blood spilt in <hi>Ireland,</hi> and cause of all the Taxes the Nation has groaned under, and above all, the Authors perhaps and Advisers of all those violent Attempts against our Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, Constitution and Laws, by which all Liberty, Sacred and Civil, was en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangered. I say, to these Men he is pleased to offer their Estates, whenever grown weary of unsuccessful Rebellion, they shall think fit to accept of them, If any thing could wean a Thinking Man from a Goverment to which Principle and Assection inclined him, it were the thoughts of what our Author proposes; it seems strange, that a Friend to this Government should think it reasonable that those (who are declared by him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>self in his Pamphlet, to <hi>Act for</hi> Rome <hi>and</hi> France <hi>in reality</hi>) though they use the late <hi>KING</hi>'s Name, should by all means have their Estates restored them again, forfeited by Act of Parliament, when those that side with King <hi>William</hi>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:205737:7"/> upon a National Bottom, for the support of the Established Religion and Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, are exposed to the Mercy of an injured King, (as he himself styles him all along) and have nothing to trust to, but the good Nature of Priests and Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>suites in success, or the Care that may be taken for them in the Treaty so of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten mentioned in this Paper, to be car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ryed on I suppose by those in that Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretaries Office who Licensed it.</p>
            <p>I shall now Conclude this tedious Let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, which will make you less impatient for my next, with this Melancholly Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flection upon the whole, that I fear this Author, and many others like him, are empowered to Act for us, just as he Writes for us.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:205737:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>